Let us come to
the concept of concurrency.
There it is
that concurrency (like
causality) always refers
to single transitions.
With the causality
we had observed
that in a Petri net two
certain transitions can stand in this relationship.
That is, that one transition is
a "necessary condition" for the other.
In concurrency, this could be even
more than two transitions that we consider.
Therefore here the definition is formulated
for any transitions t1 to tn.
So we consider a subset T'
of the set T of all transitions.
And then we can number
the transitions, for example, which
we have
picked out there.
And then, if necessary, they are
activated concurrently for a certain marking.
This is also a difference to
before, namely that the causality always simply
relates to two transitions, and
then there is a criterion that
relates to reachability
in the reachability graph.
Whereas concurrency, that
is defined for
a set of transitions
and a certain marking m.
And then the criterion
is as follows, first mathematically.
We'll see what that
means intuitively in a moment.
Mathematically, the procedure
is simply as follows
One takes these transitions t1 to
tn, which are of course different
(otherwise this would not be a
set), thus different transitions t1 to tn.
One considers in each
case their pre-weight functions.
As we remember, these
are "markings", i.e. functions from
the place set
into the natural numbers.
And you can add
them with this special plus.
We remember, that was addition, which
is a little bit like vector addition.
So where we add in places
the entries of these n pre-weight functions.
And what comes out of
that is, again, a "marking."
And we then check whether this is
less-equal than the chosen relevant marking m.
And this smaller-equal, also to remember (or
to look up in the old slides),
that meant that per place the entry
that arose here on the left side must
be smaller-equal to the entry on
the right side at the corresponding place.
So it's not about somehow
counting all the tokens in total,
it's about
a place-by-place comparison.
And if this is
fulfilled, then it means intuitively
that ultimately the marking m contains
enough tokens, at all relevant places, that
the transitions from T' (these t1
to tn) could in principle fire simultaneously.
Simultaneously in the
sense of parallel.
After all, we had already
intuitively discussed the notions of "concurrent"
and "parallel", and I had talked
about "concurrent" being the formal criterion
that would in
principle allow concurrent-parallel execution.
So relevant here is
indeed the difference to causality.
If we look again at an example
from the previous video on causality, there we
had this example and observed for example
that t1 was necessary condition for t4.
In the sense that
we had sequential dependence.
So t4, when we started like this
with this Petri net, could never be
fired if t1
was not fired before.
And that was also
true for t1 and t2.
But t2 and t3 were independent,
and in fact we will see in
a moment that t2 and t3 here
are parallel or just concurrent in certain senses.
The causality referred
to sequential order.
So, for example, t2
can never be fired
if t1 was not fired
before (because of this dependence here).
While t2 and t3 were
not dependent in this sense.
And in fact these will
be recognized as concurrent right away.
We had also looked at
this in the reachability graph.
And there the argument, for example,
for t4 depending on t1 was
that t1 is a
necessary condition for t4.
That we can never execute t4
if we haven't executed t1 first.
So there, too, it
was about sequential order.
Whereas t2, t3 just had
no such relationship to each other.
And in fact, if we look at t2
and t3 here, how they can fire out of
this marking, then we can already
sense a bit of parallelism here.
Or at least "indifference" regarding the
order and perhaps also complete independence.
Namely, we can fire t2 from
here and then t3 to get to
this marking; and obviously we
could have fired t3, t2 instead.
Why
is that?
Because basically t2 and t3
are firing completely independently here.
The t2 makes sure that
this 1 moves to here.
Yes, here in the marking you can see
that, that this 1 goes from here to here.
And t3 means that this
1 goes from here to here.
So t2 ultimately depends on this 1 here, t3
depends on this 1 here, at this position, and
these are conditions
that are completely independent.
So basically, nobody would prevent
t2 and t3 from taking this
token and this token, respectively, at the same
time, and putting that down on the last position.
What would
that mean?
That we would then
have the 2 here, (0,0,0,2).
And of course, that's what
happens down here after we fire
t2, t3
in any order.
So we'll see in a moment that actually
starting from this marking, t2 and t3 are
basically parallel, or concurrent, and
could fire simultaneously if we didn't
want to write this down
so sequentially as a reachability graph.
So this scheme here, this "diamond"
(that's also what it's called, this
shape in the reachability graph where
t2 and t3 are just so alternately
fireable), that's at least an
indication of such potentially parallel behavior.
So in this sense one could already
speak of simultaneous firing in this example.
Also
important:
We just looked at this
in a reachability graph, but
in fact this definition refers
to a concrete marking, not to
the reachability graph
as a whole.
So it's not going to be
about analyzing the reachability graph as
a whole and identifying
any properties in it.
Rather, it is always about a
concrete marking and what is possible there.
We can see here that
this condition actually refers to
this marking and not
to the reachability graph.
Okay, then one can
make another observation here,
which is very obvious
already from the intuitive understanding.
Namely, if we have such a set
of transitions whose elements are concurrent for
a given marking, then this is
also true for any subset of T'.
So, of course, we
are potentially always looking for
large sets that
are simultaneously concurrently activated.
If we have transitions t1, t2,
t3 and they are concurrently activated, then
only t1, t2 together
would also be concurrently activated.
And in particular, of course, the individual
transitions t1, t2, t3 are also activated.
It cannot be that t1,
t2, t3 are activated concurrently,
but t2 itself
is not activated.
In the end, we can already
see this from this mathematical definition.
Because if we simply ignore
some of the transitions on
the left, nothing can change
in the occurrence of this inequality.
Because if we
omit something on the
left, these terms can become at
the most still smaller in the sum.
So they remain in any
case below the chosen marking.
This is the reason why
this observation is valid, mathematically.
But we can also think about
it intuitively, for example, using the examples.
Of course, this is
only interesting from two-element sets.
So, that also a one-element
set can be concurrently activated; there is
not really something concurrently activated, if
that is n = 1.
So it is
interesting from two-element sets.
And the larger the set, the
nicer, so to speak, as an observation.
Okay, a
first example.
And in fact, this is the Petri
net, which we had also already looked
at in causality, and which I
had also just come back to.
And I had just indicated that
here t2 and t3 are activated concurrently.
However, not in
the initial constellation.
So it doesn't make sense to say
that here t2 and t3 are activated concurrently.
They are not activated
at all in this situation.
But only in the case after
t1 has fired, for example, t2
and t3 would be activated,
and that even concurrently.
But we don't talk about
"we fire this and this and
this", but we
take a concrete marking.
And that's just not the one, but the
one from the slide that I just looked at.
And then
ask ourselves:
Are t2 and t3
activated concurrently for this marking?
So for this marking,
for the start marking here,
t2 and t3 would not be activated
concurrently, because they are not even activated themselves.
But in this concrete constellation,
t2 and t3 are concurrently activated.
We can calculate
that in a moment.
We will
do that, too.
But for this
and other examples
in between, I want to demonstrate
this again in the whiteboard app.
That is, I'm going to run through this first
and two or three other examples in the app.
Where you can also
see how the tokens move.
Where we can see in each
case what is concurrent or not.
And then I'll come back
to the slides here and
run the associated
calculations in each case.